Guide to the Elena Wilson Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Elena Wilson papers
1906-1979
1972-1979
YCAL MSS 188
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
23.38
(42 boxes) + 1 portfolio
The collection consists of correspondence, literary manuscripts, printed materials, and personal and family papers documenting the life of Elena Wilson and her work as literary executor of Edmund Wilson. The bulk of the collection dates from 1972-1979, after Edmund's death; also present are a small amount of early papers and documents of Elena's family. Series I, Correspondence, includes letters from Edmund Wilson, letters of condolence received after his death, and correspondence concerning Elena's work as his literary executor. Correspondents include Leon Edel, Daniel Aaron, Simon Karlisky, and Vera Nabokova. Series II, Writings, contains materials pertaining to Letters on Literature and Politics, including drafts, proofs, and an extensive file of photocopies of letters written by Edmund Wilson. Also present are drafts of "My View From the Other Window," an essay by Elena Wilson describing her experiences living with Edmund in Talcottville, New York; writings about Edmund by others; and a memoir written by Elena Wilson's aunt, Marie Struve, describing her early life in Russia before the 1917 Revolution. Series III, Subject Files, includes biographical material about Edmund Wilson and lists of his writings. Series IV, Personal Papers, contains calendars, passports, and other legal documents. Series IV, Family Papers, consists of legal documents and biographical information about the families of Elena Wilson's parents, Georg Hermann Mumm and Olga Struve, and her first husband, James Thornton. Series VI, Helen Miranda Wilson Papers, contains documents pertaining to Elena Wilson's death, with notes made by Helen Miranda Wilson, daughter of Elena and Edmund Wilson.
Wilson, Elena, 1906-1979
Struve, Marie
Wilson, Edmund, 1895-1972
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Elena Wilson Papers were acquired through gifts of Elena Wilson, 1975 and 1977; purchases from Elena Wilson, on the Danford N. Barney, Jr., Fund, the Edwin J. Beinecke, '07, Frederick W. Beinecke, '09S, and Walter Beinecke, '10 Fund, and the Eugene G. O'Neill Memorial Fund, 1973 and 1978; a purchase from Helen Miranda Wilson on the Ezra Pound Archive Fund, 1995, and a gift of Farrar, Straus & Giroux, 1981.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Boxes 40-42 and portfolio (folders 935-937): Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
ELENA WILSON (1906-1979)
Elena Wilson was born on August 27, 1906, in Reims, France. The family of her father, Georg Hermann Mumm, were founders of Mumm's Champagne. Her mother, Olga Struve, was born in Japan, where Elena's grandfather served as Russian ambassador. During her childhood and early adulthood, Elena Mumm lived in France, Germany, and Switzerland, spoke French, German, Russian, and English, was educated by private tutors, and studied art in Munich and Paris. In her twenties, she emigrated to the United States. She married James Thornton, a Canadian businessman, in 1931, and had a son, Henry H. M. Thornton, in 1932.
During the 1930s-40s, Elena and James Thornton lived in New York, and Elena worked as an editor for Town and Country. In 1945 she met Edmund Wilson, then married to writer Mary McCarthy. Edmund's short story "Glimpses of Wilbur Flick," part of his novel Memoirs of Hecate County, was published in Town and Country in 1946. Elena's relationship with Edmund deepened during 1946. In October they went to Nevada, obtained divorces, and were married in Reno on December 11. After their marriage, Elena Wilson left Town and Country and settled with Edmund in Wellfleet, Massachusetts. Their daughter Helen Miranda Wilson was born in 1948. In Wellfleet, and later in Edmund's ancestral home in Talcottville, New York, Elena was involved in literary and social circles and managed a large household including Helen, her son Henry, and Edmund's children from previous marriages, Rosalind and Reuel.
After Edmund's death in 1972, Elena acted as his literary executor. She edited a collection of his correspondence, Letters on Literature and Politics (New York: Farrar, Straus & Giroux, 1977), and worked with Leon Edel, Simon Karlinsky, and other editors of Edmund's writings. She continued to live in Wellfleet, where she was active in political organizations, including the League of Women Voters and Amnesty International. Elena Wilson died in Wellfleet on July 27, 1979.
Scope and Contents
The Elena Wilson Papers consist of correspondence, literary manuscripts, printed materials, and personal and family papers documenting the life of Elena Wilson and her work as literary executor of her husband Edmund Wilson. The papers span the years 1906-1979, encompassing early family documents through papers relating to Elena Wilson's death. The bulk of the collection dates from 1972-1979 and relates to Elena Wilson's life and work after the death of Edmund Wilson.
The collection is housed in 42 boxes and one portfolio, and is organized into six series: Correspondence, Writings, Subject Files, Personal Papers, Family Papers, and Helen Miranda Wilson Papers. Oversize materials are stored in 9 boxes. Restricted Fragile Papers, stored in boxes 40-42 and a portfolio, contain materials for which reference photocopies have been substituted in the main files.
Series I, Correspondence, (boxes 1-8), consists of letters to Elena Wilson from business and personal correspondents, with a small amount of outgoing carbons interfiled. The bulk of this series consists of letters from Edmund Wilson to Elena, 1946-1969, and correspondence after Edmund's death concerning Elena's work as his literary executor. Also present are letters of condolence sent to Elena on Edmund's death, letters to Elena from her children, Henry H. M. Thornton and Helen Miranda Wilson, and letters from friends and European relatives. Other letters addressed to both Elena and Edmund, as well as Elena's letters to Edmund, are in the Edmund Wilson Papers (YCAL MSS 187).
Edmund's letters to Elena date from 1946, shortly after they met, through the last years of Edmund's life. During April-September, 1946, Edmund wrote frequently, often daily or several times per week, discussing plans for their divorces and marriage, and describing his family and social life in Wellfleet. Later correspondence consists of intermittent groups of detailed letters written during periods when they were apart, including European trips made by Elena, time spent by Edmund alone in Talcottville, and Edmund's trips to the Southwest, 1947, Haiti, 1949, Red Bank, during his mother's last illness, 1950, the Middle East, 1954 and 1967, and Europe, 1956. Also present are undated items, including many valentine and birthday cards.
Correspondence relating to Elena's work as editor of Letters on Literature and Politics includes letters from collaborators Leon Edel and Daniel Aaron, who contributed a foreword and introduction respectively, publisher Farrar, Straus & Giroux, and correspondents represented in the Letters, their surviving family members, and repositories holding their papers. Much of this correspondence concerns solicitation of the photocopies of Edmund's letters filed in the Writings series. Other correspondence about Edmund Wilson's writings includes letters from Leon Edel about the publication of Edmund's journals, and letters from Vera Nabokova, Simon Karlinsky, and Harper & Row about Karlinsky's edition of Edmund's correspondence with Vladimir Nabokov. Also present are letters from friends and readers responding to Letters on Literature and Politics, requests for access to Wilson's papers, requests for permission to quote from his works, fan mail, and corrections from readers received after Edmund's death.
Series II, Writings (boxes 9-27), is organized into three subseries: Letters on Literature and Politics, Other Writings, and Writings by Others. The largest part of the Letters on Literature and Politics subseries consists of photocopies of Edmund's letters collected by Elena. A few correspondents are represented by Edmund's original letters or transcripts of them; these are identified in folder titles. For some correspondents, photocopies of letters to Edmund are also present. In most cases, materials are accompanied by notes made by Elena about the content of the letters and owners of the originals. Many of Edmund's major correspondents are represented, as well as lesser known names whose correspondence highlights themes in the Letters. Large files are present for Alfred Raymond Bellinger, John Peale Bishop, Louise Bogan, Clelia Carroll, Malcolm Cowley, W. Stanley Dell, John Dos Passos, F. Scott Fitzgerald, Christian Frederick Gauss, Maxwell David Geismar, Mamaine Koestler, H. L. Mencken, Arthur Mizener, Helen Muchnic, Vladimir Nabokov, The New Yorker, Maxwell E. Perkins, Roger W. Straus, Allen Tate, Philippe Thoby-Marcelin, and Morton Dauwen Zabel. Folder titles assigned by Elena Wilson have been retained, with some standardization of name forms and the addition of cross references. Date spans following names of correspondents in folder titles are the dates of Edmund Wilson's original letters; date spans following folder titles indicate when photocopies and accompanying notes were made.
Background Materials for Letters on Literature and Politics include biographical information about Edmund Wilson and lists and an index card file of correspondent names. Other Materials consist of drafts, a setting copy, proofs corrected by Elena Wilson and Daniel Aaron, lists of corrections, reviews, and related correspondence.
The Other Writings subseries includes drafts of an essay written by Elena Wilson, "My View From the Other Window," describing her experiences living with Edmund in Talcottville, New York, and offering a viewpoint in contrast to Edmund's appreciative description of his ancestral home in his book Upstate. Other materials are notes, including notebooks kept by Elena during her Greek language studies, 1972-1979.
Most Writings by Others concern Edmund Wilson and his work, including essays and lectures by Daniel Aaron, Lewis M. Dabney, and Leon Edel, and contracts and draft materials for Simon Karlinsky's The Wilson-Nabokov Letters. Also present is a memoir written by Elena Wilson's aunt, Marie ("Maroussia") Struve, describing her early life in Russia before the 1917 Revolution.
Series III, Subject Files (box 28), is organized into two subseries: Edmund Wilson and Other Subjects. Edmund Wilson files include biographical information, lists of copyright status of his books, lists of essays written for The New Republic, brief notes concerning visitors at Wellfleet after his death, an obituary, and other clippings. Files for Other Subjects contain clippings, postcards, and a printed book about André Lhote, an artist with whom Elena studied in the 1920s.
Series IV, Personal Papers (box 29), contains a birth certificate, calendars, passports, financial records, and documents relating to Elena's divorce from James Thornton. Passports bear photographs of Elena Wilson and Helen Miranda Wilson as a child. Other photographs of Elena Wilson and her children are in the Edmund Wilson Papers (YCAL MSS 187).
Series V, Family Papers (box 30), is organized into three subseries: Mumm Family, Struve Family, and Thornton Family. These materials include a marriage contract made by Elena's parents Hermann Mumm and Olga Struve, genealogical information and clippings about the Mumm and Struve families, biographical information about James Thornton, and a copy of Henry H. M. Thornton's birth certificate and a clipping about his marriage.
Series VI, Helen Miranda Wilson Papers (box 30), contains an obituary for Elena Wilson and copies of her death certificate and will. In addition, explanatory notes written by Helen Miranda Wilson are appended to documents filed in other series.
Oversize (boxes 31-39) contains oversize materials from all series.
Restricted Fragile (boxes 40-42) and Restricted Fragile Oversize (portfolio), contain fragile originals for which preservation photocopies have been substituted in the main files.
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Soviet Union -- History -- Revolution, 1917-1921; Talcottville (N.Y.); Aaron, Daniel, 1912-2016; Edel, Leon, 1907-1997; Karlinsky, Simon, 1924-2009; Nabokova, Vera; Wilson, Edmund, 1895-1972; Wilson, Elena, 1906-1979; Wilson, Helen Miranda, 1948-; Mumm family; Struve family; Thornton family
- Correspondence, 1931-1979; Series I; 3.13; (8 boxes)
  - A-Z General, 1972-79, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1-8)
  - Aaron, Daniel, 1974-78, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Related Archival Materials note
    See also: Farrar, Straus & Giroux, boxes 2-3, folders 88-101
    See also: Writings/ Letters on Literature and Politics /Photocopies of Edmund Wilson Correspondence: Brinnin, John Malcolm, box 12, folder 367
    See also: Brinnin, John Malcolm, box 12, folder 367
    See also: Davison, Peter, box 13, folder 399
    See also: Hecht, Tony, box 15, folder 455
    See also: Wright, Richard, box 21, folder 622
  - Aiken, Mary Augusta Hoover, 1975, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Allilueva, Svetlana, 1972-78 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Alsop, Joseph Wright, 1974 Mar (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Amen, Marion, 1972-73 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Amherst College, 1973-74 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Anderson, Valborg, 1974-75 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Anthony, Robert O., 1974 Nov 19 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Arbasino, Alberto, 1978 Oct 18 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Atlantic Monthly Press
    See: Aaron, Daniel, box 1, folder 9
  - Atlas, James, n.y. Nov 17 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Auden, W. H. (Wystan Hugh), 1972, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Baker, Carlos, 1974 Mar 18 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Balascheff family, 1972, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Ballot, Jeanne, 1975 Feb 3 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library (Yale University), 1973-74 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Berlin, Isaiah, 1972-74, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Berman, Sylvia, 1972 Jun-Jul (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes Berman, Leonid
  - Berryman, Kathleen Donahue, 1974 Jul-Sep (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Betjeman, John, Sir, 1974 Nov 15 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Biggs, John, 1972-77 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Bishop, Alison, 1974 Jul 12 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Bishop, Alison M. K., 1974 Nov 27 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Bishop, Jonathan, 1975-77, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Blais, Marie Claire, 1972-75, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Bliven, Bruce
    See: Edel, Leon, box 2, folders 77-80
  - Bode, Carl, 1972-73 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Bowen, William G., 1977 May (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Bowers, Fredson, 1976 Sep (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Branch, Edgar Marquess, 1975 May (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Brandon, Henry (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Branscomb, Lewis C., 1974 Oct-Nov (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Bruccoli, Matthew Joseph, 1974-77 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Brunauer, Dalma Hunyadi, 1973-74 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Buffington, Robert, 1978 Sep (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Bulgheroni, Marisa, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Bulkin, Eleanor, 1972-73 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Bunker, Robert Manson, 1972 Jul 14 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Cabell, Margaret Freeman, 1974 Dec 9 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Callaghan, Barry, 1972-73 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Canby, James B., 3rd, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Capellán, Angel, 1975 Nov 11 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Carr, Virginia Spencer, 1977-78 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Carter, Jimmy, 1977-78 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Cartier-Bresson, Henri, 1972-77 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Charles Scribner's Sons, 1973-75 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Chavchavadze, Marina, 1972 Jul 26 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Chermayeff, Barbara, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Colebrook, Joan, 1978-79 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Columbia University Libraries, 1973-74 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Connor, Louise, 1972 June 17 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Cornell University Libraries, 1974 Feb-May (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Costa, Richard Hauer, 1972, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Cowley, Malcolm, 1972-74 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Crosten, Loran, 1972-74 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Crosten, Mary, 1974 May-Now (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Dabney, Lewis M., 1974-78 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Davis, Linda H., 1978 Feb-Jul (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Davison, Peter
  - De Voto, Avis, 1974 May 13 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Dell, W. Stanley, 1974 Dec 16 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Deming, Barbara, 1972-74, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Deutsch, Babette, 1973-74 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Di Spirito, Henry, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Didion, Joan, 1972-75 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Diggins, John P., 1972-75 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Donaldson, Scott, 1978 Feb 28 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Dos Passos, Elizabeth Hamlin Holdridge, 1972-73, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Duganne, Phyllis
    See: Given, Eben, box 4, folder 119
  - Dunton, E. Aenid, 1973 Jul-Dec (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Dupee, F. W. (Frederick Wilcox), 1974 May-Jun (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Dworsky, Suzanne Rufenacht Hughes, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Edel, Leon, 1972-79, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 77-80)
  - Edmonds, Walter Dumaux, 1973 Mar (Box 2, Folder 81)
  - Edmunds, Lowell, 1976 Mar-Apr (Box 2, Folder 82)
  - Eliot, Valerie, 1974 Apr-Jun (Box 2, Folder 83)
  - Ellmann, Richard, 1974-75 (Box 2, Folder 84)
  - Encounter, 1974 Jan 6 (Box 2, Folder 85)
  - Epstein, Barbara
    See: New York Review of Books, box 5, folder 195
  - Epstein, Jason, 1976 Apr 30 (Box 2, Folder 86)
    See also: Wilson, Rosalind Baker, box 8, folder 307
  - Farrar, John Chipman, 1972 Jun 16 (Box 2, Folder 87)
  - Farrar. Strais & Giroux, 1972-75 (Box 2, Folder 88-89)
  - Farrar, Straus & Giroux, 1975-78 (Box 3, Folder 90-98)
    See also: Writings/ Letters on Literature and Politics /Other Materials/Lists of corrections by Farrar, Straus & Giroux, box 25, folder 672
  - Farrar, Straus & Giroux, 1978-79, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 99-101)
  - Farrell, James T. (James Thomas), 1972-74 (Box 3, Folder 102)
  - Fassett, Stephen B., 1978 Jan 16 (Box 3, Folder 103)
  - Felstiner, John, 1974 Apr 29 (Box 3, Folder 104)
  - Fenton, William Nelson, 1972-73 (Box 3, Folder 105)
  - Field, Andrew, 1974, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 106)
  - Firmage, George James, 1976 Feb-Mar (Box 3, Folder 107)
  - Fitzgerald, Robert, 1974 Nov 16 (Box 4, Folder 108)
  - Flanner, Janet, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 109)
  - Flint, Robert, 1972-77 (Box 4, Folder 110)
  - Flory, Margaret A., 1974 Jul 28 (Box 4, Folder 111)
  - Flynn, Thomas F., 1978 Jul (Box 4, Folder 112)
  - Foley, Ivan M., Jr., 1976-77, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 113)
  - Frank, Charles P., 1971-72 (Box 4, Folder 114)
  - Friedman, B. H. (Bernard Harper), 1974 Apr 22 (Box 4, Folder 115)
  - Gallup, Donald Clifford
    See: Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, box 1, folder 23
  - Gardner, Helen, 1974 May (Box 4, Folder 116)
  - Geismar, Maxwell David, 1972-77 (Box 4, Folder 117)
  - Gilliatt, Penelope, 1972, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 118)
  - Giroux, Robert
    See: Farrar, Straus & Giroux, boxes 2-3, folders 88-101
  - Given, Eben, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 119)
  - Goodman, Celia, 1972-77 (Box 4, Folder 120)
  - Gotham Book Mart, 1972-76 (Box 4, Folder 121)
  - Gould, Helen May, 1972 Jun 12 (Box 4, Folder 122)
  - Grynberg, Sonia, 1972, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 123)
  - Hackett, Mary, 1978 Feb 9 (Box 4, Folder 124)
  - Halper, Nathan, 1978 Aug 5 (Box 4, Folder 125)
  - Hamburger, Philip, 1972 Jun 20 (Box 4, Folder 126)
  - Harcourt Brace Jovanovich, 1974-77 (Box 4, Folder 127)
  - Harper & Row, Publishers, 1975-79, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 128)
    See also: Karlinsky, Simon, box 4, folders 149-150
  - Hart-Davis, Rupert, 1974 Mar-May (Box 4, Folder 129)
  - Hartmann, Georg T.
  - Hatch, Robert
    See: The Nation, box box 5, folder 193
  - Hawthorne, Hazel, 1972-74 (Box 4, Folder 130)
  - Hayward, Max, 1972 Jun 15 (Box 4, Folder 131)
  - Hearne, John, 1972 Aug 12 (Box 4, Folder 132)
  - Hellmann, Lillian, 1973-79 (Box 4, Folder 133)
  - Hemingway, Mary Welsh, 1974 Mar 4 (Box 4, Folder 134)
  - Herzog, Lily, 1978, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 135)
  - Heuser, Mignonne, 1972 Jun 13 (Box 4, Folder 136)
  - Highet, Gilbert, 1975 Sep 21 (Box 4, Folder 137)
  - Hoopes, Roy, 1978 Jul 28 (Box 4, Folder 138)
  - Horgan, Paul, 1972-77 (Box 4, Folder 139)
  - Houghton Library (Harvard University), 1973-74 (Box 4, Folder 140)
  - Howe, Irving, 1972, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 141)
  - Howe, Thalia, 1972 Sep 3 (Box 4, Folder 142)
  - Hughes, H. Stuart (Henry Stuart), 1976, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 143)
  - Ingram Merrill Foundation, 1975 Jul (Box 4, Folder 144)
  - Isernhagen, Hartwig, 1978 May (Box 4, Folder 145)
  - Jackson, Katherine Gauss, 1972, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 146)
  - Jarrell, Mary, 1975 Oct 14 (Box 4, Folder 147)
  - Jolas, Maria, 1975 Jan 27 (Box 4, Folder 148)
  - Karlinsky, Simon, 1976-79 (Box 4, Folder 149-150)
    See also: Harper & Row, Publishers, box 4, folder 128
    See also: Nabokova, Vera, box 5, folder 192
    See also: Princeton University Press, box 5, folder 216
  - Kazin, Alfred, 1972-77, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 151)
  - Kennan, George, 1974 Sep 26 (Box 4, Folder 152)
  - Kern, Edith, 1975 Jan 15 (Box 4, Folder 153)
  - Killorin, Joseph, 1974 Dec 12 (Box 4, Folder 154)
  - Kline, George Louis, 1973 Nov 1 (Box 4, Folder 155)
  - Kogan, Herman, 1978, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 156)
  - Krementz, Jill, 1972 Jun 21 (Box 4, Folder 157)
  - Kretzoi, Charlotte, 1972 Jun 24 (Box 4, Folder 158)
    Includes Kretzoi, Miklósné
  - Kriegel, Leonard, 1974 Feb-Aug (Box 4, Folder 159)
  - Kronenberger, Louis, 1972-73 (Box 4, Folder 160)
  - Landau, Jacob, 1972-79 (Box 4, Folder 161)
  - Lang, Cecil Y., 1972-77 (Box 4, Folder 162)
  - Lasky, Melvin J.
    See: Encounter, box 2, folder 85
  - Lehovich, Dimitry V., 1974-75 (Box 4, Folder 163)
  - Levin, Harry, 1974-75 (Box 4, Folder 164)
  - Library of Congress, 1973-74, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 165)
  - Limmer, Ruth, 1972-77 (Box 4, Folder 166)
  - Link, Carolyn Crosby Wilson, 1972 Jun 17 (Box 4, Folder 167)
  - Loos, Anita, 1972-77 (Box 4, Folder 168)
  - Lowell, Robert, 1972, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 169)
  - Ludington, Townsend, 1972-74, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 170)
  - McCarthy, Mary, 1972, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 171)
  - MacDonald, Michael C. D., 1972 Sep 20 (Box 4, Folder 172)
  - McGovern, George S. (George Stanley), 1972 Jun 21 (Box 4, Folder 173)
  - MacLennan, Hugh, 1972, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 174)
  - McWilliams, Carey
    See: The Nation, box 5, folder 193
  - McWilliams, Iris
  - Malraux, André, 1974 Mar 20 (Box 4, Folder 175)
  - Matthews, T. S. (Thomas Stanley), 1972-74 (Box 5, Folder 176)
  - Meigs, Mary, 1972, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 177)
  - Mele, Bette Crouse, 1975, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 178)
    Includes a photograph of Mele, Antonio Edmund Wilson
  - Mellon, Emily Emig, 1977 Apr-Aug (Box 5, Folder 179)
    See also: Sheed, Wilfrid, box 6, folder 239
  - Mendelson, Edward, 1975, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 180)
  - Mendenhall, Thomas C. (Thomas Corwin), 1972, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 181)
  - Mestchersky-Shuvalov, Marina, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 182)
  - Milford, Nancy, 1972-78 (Box 5, Folder 183)
  - Mizener, Arthur, 1976-77 (Box 5, Folder 184)
  - Moore, Benita A., 1976 Feb-May (Box 5, Folder 185)
  - Morris, Glyn, 1972-77 (Box 5, Folder 186)
  - Muchnic, Helen, 1972-78 (Box 5, Folder 187)
  - Mumford, Lewis, 1975 Jun 14 (Box 5, Folder 188)
  - Murphy, Noël, n.y. Dec 18 (Box 5, Folder 189)
  - Myers, Margaret Cochran Bishop, 1975-76, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 190)
  - Nabokov, Nicolas, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 191)
  - Nabokova, Vera, 1972-77 (Box 5, Folder 192)
    See also: Harper & Row, Publishers, box box 4, folder 128
  - The Nation, 1973 Oct-Dec (Box 5, Folder 193)
  - New York Public Library, 1973-75 (Box 5, Folder 194)
  - New York Review of Books, 1973-77, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 195)
  - The New Yorker, 1973-75 (Box 5, Folder 196)